<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../Balisage-1-3-rng/balisage-1-3.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="balisage-proceedings-html.xsl"?>
<article xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
    <title>The integration of XML databases and content management systems in digital
        editions</title>
    <subtitle>Understanding eXist-db through Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups</subtitle>
    <info>
        <abstract>
            <para>We have identified four models for integrating digital edition content into
                eXist-db [<xref linkend="eXist-db"/>], which are, in decreasing order of eXist-db
                dependence: 1) TEI Publisher [<xref linkend="teiPublisher"/>], 2) the eXist-db app
                framework using HTML templating [<xref linkend="templating"/>], 3) the eXist-db app
                framework without HTML templating [<xref linkend="webapp"/>] (similar to Joe
                Wicentowski's Punch project [<xref linkend="punch"/>]), and 4) using Apache [<xref
                    linkend="apache"/>] and PHP [<xref linkend="php"/>] to mediate between the user
                and eXist-db, so that eXist-db provides only XML database services. Our presentation
                will examine and compare these ways of conceptualizing and implementing the
                infrastructure for a digital edition. Each of them has advantages and disadvantages,
                primarily from the perspective of sustainability, and those concerns apply to
                edition frameworks generally, and are therefore not specific to eXist-db.</para>
        </abstract>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>David</firstname>
                <othername>J.</othername>
                <surname>Birnbaum</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>David J. Birnbaum is Professor and Chair of the Department of Slavic Languages
                    and Literatures at the University of Pittsburgh. He has been involved in the
                    study of electronic text technology since the mid-1980s, has delivered
                    presentations at a variety of electronic text technology conferences, and has
                    served on the board of the Association for Computers and the Humanities, the
                    editorial board of <emphasis role="ital">Markup languages: theory and
                        practice</emphasis>, and the Text Encoding Initiative Technical Council.
                    Much of his electronic text work intersects with his research in medieval Slavic
                    manuscript studies, but he also often writes about issues in the philosophy of
                    markup.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Professor and Chair</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Department of Slavic Languages and Literatures, University of Pittsburgh
                    (US)</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>djbpitt@gmail.com</email>
            <link>http://www.obdurodon.org</link>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Leif-Jöran</firstname>
                <surname>Olsson</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Leif-Jöran Olsson has been employed since 2005 as a systems developer at
                    Språkbanken, the Swedish Language bank, University of Gothenburg, where he
                    develops research infrastructure for language technology, both nationally and
                    within CLARIN ERIC. His project management experience involves both long-term
                    partner projects (e.g., the Swedish Literary Bank, the Selma Lagerlöf Archive,
                    the Swedish Drama web) and short-term domain-specific toolboxes (including
                    training and use case analysis). He has extensive experience with teaching in
                    language technology and programming. Leif-Jöran obtained his MA in Language
                    Technology from Uppsala University in 2004, and he is one of the core developers
                    of the open-source eXist-db native XML database.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Systems developer</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Språkbanken, Department of Swedish, University of Gothenburg
                    (Sweden)</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>leif-joran.olsson@svenska.gu.se</email>
            <link>https://spraakbanken.gu.se/personal/ljo</link>
        </author>
        <author>
            <personname>
                <firstname>Joseph</firstname>
                <surname>Wicentowski</surname>
            </personname>
            <personblurb>
                <para>Joseph Wicentowski is a historian who specializes in the use of open standards
                    to improve the accessibility and utility of scholarly editions. Since completing
                    his Ph.D. in History at Harvard University in 2007, he has spearheaded a project
                    to convert a major diplomatic documentary edition to TEI, leveraging the XML
                    family of technologies to enable editors, researchers, and the public to access
                    texts online in multiple open formats. Wicentowski has led workshops on the
                    XQuery language and the eXist-db open source native XML database at TEI@Oxford
                    Summer School in 2010–11 and Digital Humanities 2017, serves as a community
                    liaison for the eXist-db community, and is co-author of a forthcoming book on
                    XQuery for digital humanists in the Coding for Humanists series from Texas
                    A&amp;M University Press.</para>
            </personblurb>
            <affiliation>
                <jobtitle>Digital History Advisor</jobtitle>
                <orgname>Office of the Historian, US Department of State</orgname>
            </affiliation>
            <email>joewiz@gmail.com</email>
            <link>https://github.com/joewiz</link>
        </author>
    </info>
    <section>
        <title>Introduction</title>
        <para>In the 1980s Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups, long owned by the Hershey Corporation and one
            of the best selling and most popular candy products in the US (<xref linkend="upton"/>),
            deployed an advertising campaign that portrayed the idea of eating chocolate and peanut
            butter together as a serendipitous pleasure. In one television advertisement (<xref
                linkend="reeses"/>), two persons accidentally walk into each other on the street, he
            eating a chocolate bar and she (perhaps surprisingly) eating peanut butter out of a jar
            with her finger. They collide, the chocolate bar winds up embedded in the peanut butter,
            and they protest, in unison: <quote>You got your chocolate in my peanut butter"</quote>
            and <quote>You got peanut butter on my chocolate!</quote> They both then,
            simultaneously, realize that they like the taste of the combination, and proclaim, still
            in unison, <quote>Delicious!</quote>, as an older man (apparently a grocer; he wears an
            apron) suddenly materializes between them, standing uncomfortably close and silently
            ogling the packaged Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups that he holds up (for the camera; it is
            behind the field of view of the two principals).</para>
        <figure xml:id="reeses_image" xreflabel="Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups (commercial; product)">
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="jpg" fileref="reeses.jpg" width="49%"/>
                </imageobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="reeses-wrappers.jpg" width="49%"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Meanwhile, in a galaxy far, far away, the eXist-db XML database was born in <emphasis
                role="bold">[EXPAND]</emphasis>. Since its inception, eXist-db has provided the
            services one expects from any database management system (DBMS): it stores records (XML
            documents), builds persistent indexes, supports retrieval with a query language
            (XQuery), and provides the housekeeping functionality (e.g., user authentication) those
            processes require. We might consider this functionality as analogous to the peanut
            butter center of a Reese’s Peanut Butter Cup. eXist-db is commonly hosted inside an HTTP
            server and servlet container (it ships with <xref linkend="Jetty"/>, but other hosts are
            also supported), which mediates between the user and the eXist-db functionality, as is
            illustrated in this image from <xref linkend="exist-book"/>:</para>
        <figure xml:id="exist-book-jetty"
            xreflabel="eXist web applicaation  platform architecture (Siegel and Retter 2014: 72)">
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata format="jpg" fileref="jetty.jpg"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>
        <para>Since its early years users have been able to interact with eXist-db by communicating
            directly with the Jetty server, and over time eXist-db has increasingly come to support
            features that are more commonly associated with a Content Management System (CMS) than
            with a database, such as themes, templates, and page management (not just data resource
            management). We might consider eXist-db CMS services as analogous to the chocolate shell
            of a Reese’s Peanut Butter Cup. Peanut butter and chocolate have a long history as
            independently popular foodstuffs, and neither depends in any necessary, obvious, or even
            intuitive way on the other, yet their combination in a single product has proven
            impressively popular with consumers. Similarly, there is nothing about a DBMS that
            requires or expects CMS services, and vice versa, yet the growing integration of the two
            types of functionality within eXist-db confirms that they can be combined to create a
            resource for developing and deploying digital editions.</para>
        <para>With the release of TEI Publisher 4.0 in December 2018 [<xref
                linkend="teiPublisher4.0"/>], built on a Web Components foundation [<xref
                linkend="webComponents"/>], eXist-db can be said to provide a hosting platform for
            digital editions that goes beyond traditional DBMS services:<blockquote>
                <para>Despite its elegant simplicity, various projects we realized in the past prove
                    that the TEI Processing Model is: <blockquote>
                        <para>1. powerful enough to cover complex transformation needs</para>
                        <para>2. a truly universal tool for any kind of digital edition</para>
                        <para> 3. efficient and as fast (or faster) as handwritten
                            transformations</para>
                        <para>4. suitable for any XML, not just TEI (this documentation is written
                            in docbook!)</para>
                    </blockquote> However, online editions require more than just a text
                    transformation: the text needs to be embedded into an application context,
                    adding navigation, pagination, search, facsimile display and so on. The larger
                    part of TEI Publisher deals with those aspects, providing all the necessary
                    building blocks for an online edition. [<xref linkend="teiPublisherQuick"
                    />]</para>
            </blockquote></para>
        <para>After a digression about model—view—controller (MVC) architecture, which serves as a
            reference point for comparison and discussion, in the following sections we describe
            four models for integrating digital edition content into eXist-db. These are, in
            increasing order of eXist-db dependence: <orderedlist>
                <listitem>
                    <para>using Apache [<xref linkend="apache"/>] and PHP [<xref linkend="php"/>] to
                        mediate between the user and eXist-db, so that eXist-db provides only XML
                        database services;</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the eXist-db app framework without HTML templating [<xref linkend="webapp"
                        />];</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>the eXist-db app framework using HTML templating [<xref
                            linkend="templating"/>]; and</para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>TEI Publisher [<xref linkend="teiPublisher"/>].</para>
                </listitem>
            </orderedlist> Each of these ways of conceptualizing and implementing the infrastructure
            for a digital edition has advantages and disadvantages, primarily from the perspective
            of sustainability, and those concerns also apply to edition frameworks generally, and
            are therefore not specific to eXist-db.</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Model—View—Controller architecture (MVC)</title>
        <para>blah blah blah</para>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Four ways of building an edition with eXist-db</title>
        <section>
            <title>PHP</title>
            <para>blah blah blah</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Apps without HTML templating</title>
            <para>blah blah blah</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Apps with HTML templating</title>
            <para>blah blah blah</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>TEI Publisher</title>
            <para>blah blah blah</para>
        </section>
    </section>
    <section>
        <title>Conclusion</title>
        <para>blah blah blah</para>
    </section>
    <bibliography>
        <title>Works cited</title>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="apache" xreflabel="Apache"><quote>Apache HTTP server project.</quote>
            <link>https://httpd.apache.org</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="eXist-db" xreflabel="eXist-db"><quote>eXist-db.</quote>
            <link>http://exist-db.org</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="templating" xreflabel="eXist-db HTML templating"><quote>eXist-db: HTML
                Templating Module.</quote>
            <link>http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/templating.xml</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="webapp" xreflabel="eXist-db Web application"><quote>eXist-db: Getting
                started with Web application development.</quote>
            <link>http://exist-db.org/exist/apps/doc/development-starter</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="Jetty" xreflabel="Jetty">Eclipse Jetty.
                <link>https://www.eclipse.org/jetty/</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="php" xreflabel="PHP"><quote>PHP: hypertext preprocessor.</quote>
            <link>https://www.php.net/</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="punch" xreflabel="Punch">Wicentowski, Joe. <quote>Punch. A simple
                application written in XQuery for eXist demonstrating how to create a dynamic,
                searchable website for TEI text.</quote>
            <link>https://github.com/joewiz/punch</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="reeses" xreflabel="Reese’s"><quote>Vintage 80s Reese’s peanut butter
                cups commercial with walkers.</quote>
            <link>https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DJLDF6qZUX0</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="exist-book" xreflabel="Siegel and Retter 2014">Siegel, Erik and Adam
            Retter. <emphasis role="ital">eXist. A NoSQL document database and application
                platform.</emphasis> Sebastopol, CA: O’Reilly. 2014.</bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="teiPublisher" xreflabel="TEI Publisher"><quote>TEI publisher.</quote>
            <link>https://teipublisher.com</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="teiPublisher4.0" xreflabel="TEI Publisher 4.0"><quote>TEI Publisher
                4.0.</quote> Product announcement. 2018-12-20.
                <link>https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/blog/tei-publisher-40.xml</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="teiPublisherQuick" xreflabel="TEI Publisher Quickstart"><quote>TEI
                Publisher Quickstart.</quote>
            <link>https://teipublisher.com/exist/apps/tei-publisher/doc/documentation.xml</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="upton" xreflabel="Upton 2013">Upton, Emily. <quote>The fascinating rise
                of Reese’s Peanut Butter Cups.</quote>
            <emphasis role="ital">Business insider.</emphasis> June 30, 2013.
                <link>https://www.businessinsider.com/the-fascinating-rise-of-reeses-peanut-butter-cups-2013-6</link></bibliomixed>
        <bibliomixed xml:id="webComponents" xreflabel="Web Components">webcomponents.org.
                <quote>Introduction.</quote>
            <link>https://www.webcomponents.org/introduction</link></bibliomixed>
    </bibliography>
</article>
